<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="docbook.css"?>

<!-- nerd=Slang 1. A foolish, inept, or unattractive person.  2. A person who is single-minded or accomplished in scientific or technical pursuits but is felt to be socially inept. = ortopédico/soso/paria inteligente
popular = 
cheerleaders =
candid=1. Free from prejudice; impartial.  2. Characterized by openness and sincerity of expression; unreservedly straightforward: In private, I gave them my candid opinion.
retard (noun)=¿retrasados?
outcast=One that has been excluded from a society or system. -> condenar al ostracismo
break ranks= (Military) to fall out of line, esp when under attack
to humour=vb (tr) 10. to attempt to gratify; indulge: he humoured the boy's whims.  11. to adapt oneself to: to humour someone's fantasies. 
navy seals=The United States Navy's Sea, Air, Land Teams, commonly known as the Navy SEALs, are the U.S. Navy's principal special operations force and a part of the Naval Special Warfare Command and United States Special Operations Command.
slacker (n.) = 1. One who shirks work or responsibility: "In terms of their outlook on the future, slackers regard tomorrow with a studied cynicism or . . . don't even conceive of one" (Julie Caniglia).
conformist =  A person who uncritically or habitually conforms to the customs, rules, or styles of a group.

fi·nesse  (fə-nĕs′)
n.
1. Refinement and delicacy of performance, execution, or artisanship.
2. Skillful, subtle handling of a situation; tactful, diplomatic maneuvering.
3. A method of leading up to a tenace, as in bridge, in order to prevent an opponent from winning the trick with an intermediate card.
4. A stratagem in which one appears to decline an advantage.
v. fi·nessed, fi·ness·ing, fi·ness·es
v.tr.
1. To accomplish by the use of finesse.
2. To handle with a deceptive or evasive strategy.
3. To play (a card) as a finesse.

awkward = 1. Not graceful; ungainly. 2. a. Not dexterous; clumsy.

crude = 1. Being in an unrefined or natural state; raw. 2. Lacking tact or taste; blunt or offensive: a crude, mannerless oaf; a crude remark. 3. Characterized by uncultured simplicity; lacking in sophistication or subtlety: had only a crude notion of how a computer works.

nadir =  The lowest point: the nadir of their fortunes.

plea =1. An earnest request; an appeal: spoke out in a plea for greater tolerance.

dwell on = a. To fasten one's attention: kept dwelling on what went wrong. See Synonyms at brood.
b. To speak or write at length; expatiate: dwelt on the need to trim the budget.

warp = 2. To turn from a correct or proper course; deflect. 3. To affect unfavorably, unfairly, or wrongly; bias. 

pervasive = Having the quality or tendency to pervade or permeate: the pervasive odor of garlic. = oprimente?

barbaric = 2. Marked by crudeness or lack of restraint in taste, style, or manner.

pick on = meterse con

society wife = dama de sociedad
Ladies who lunch is a phrase often used to describe well-off, well-dressed women who meet for social luncheons, usually during the working week. Typically, the women involved are married and non-working. Normally the lunch is in a high-class restaurant, but could also take place in a department store during a shopping trip. Sometimes the lunch takes place under the pretext of raising money for charity.

pep rally = elevación/subida de moral
Pep rallies are events that occur primarily[citation needed] in the United States and Canada. A pep rally is a gathering of people, typically students of middle school, high school and college age, before a sports event. The purpose of such a gathering is to encourage school spirit and to support members of the team for which the rally is being thrown. The pep rallies are often very loud and have a lot of excitation to keep all the students excited for the upcoming game and to cheer on the team.

Twinkie = Twinkie is a racial pejorative used by most American Indians to refer to a European American, with little or no social or blood links to any tribe, who claims to be an American Indian. Particularly applies to those who claim to be shaman, healers, or other prominent respected positions in Indian culture. They frequently request money or donations to become part of their organization or to attend ceremonies. They sometimes have websites full of mismatched and/or incorrect symbols and facts borrowed from books or pop culture images of Indian culture. Many of these groups essentially sell fraudulent ceremonies and feel-good ideas. They try to incorporate New Age ideas such as "Energy Healing", "Atlantis" and Tantric sex into a fanciful Native American spirituality. = chamán blanco

nursery = 1. A room or area in a household set apart for the use of children. 2. a. A place for the temporary care of children in the absence of their parents.

balk = 1. To stop short and refuse to go on: The horse balked at the jump. 2. To refuse obstinately or abruptly: She balked at the very idea of compromise.

cocktail = engendro

messed up

per·cen·tile  (pər-sĕn′tīl′) n. One of a set of points on a scale arrived at by dividing a group into parts in order of magnitude. For example, a score equal to or greater than 97 percent of those attained on an examination is said to be in the 97th percentile.

11/25 of 274

-->


<section>
<title>Por qué los raros no caen bien en el colegio</title>
<!-- From "HACKERS & PAINTERS
  Big Ideas from the Computer Age"
  by Paul Graham
  O'Reilly 2004 -->
<para>En la Secundaria Obligatoria mi amigo Rich y yo hicimos un estudio de dónde nos sentábamos en el comedor según popularidad. Nos resultó muy fácil dado que los alumnos sólo compartían mesa con otros de igual popularidad. Las clasificamos de la A a la E. En las A se sentaban jugadores de rugby, sus animadoras y demás. En las E estaban los casos menores de síndrome de Down, que en aquella época llamábamos «retrasados».</para>
<para>Nosotros nos sentábamos en una mesa D, lo más bajo entre los que no padecíamos defectos físicos evidentes. Y no era ingenuo por nuestra parte el clasificarnos D. Mentiríamos descaradamente de haberlo negado ya que todos los niños del colegio conocíamos perfectamente el grado de popularidad de cada uno, incluido el de uno mismo.</para>
<para>Conozco a muchos que en la escuela han sido raros. Todos cuentan la misma historia: que hay una fuerte correlación entre inteligencia y ser tenido por raro, y una correlación inversa aún más fuerte entre ser un raro y no caer bien. La inteligencia te <emphasis>hace</emphasis> caer mal.</para>
<para>¿Por qué? Al que está en edad escolar le parecerá una pregunta absurda ya que la situación es tan extrema que cuesta imaginar que la cosa pudiera ser de otra manera. Pero podría. Ser inteligente no le convertía a uno en un paria en la escuela primaria, ni tampoco perjudica en el mundo real. Ni tampoco es tan grave el problema en la mayoría de los demás países. Pero en la típica escuela secundaria de EEUU ser listo probablemente te cree problemas. ¿Por qué?</para>

  <!-- vertical space -->
<para>La solución del misterio se encuentra en formular la pregunta de modo ligeramente diferente. ¿Por qué los niños inteligentes no consiguen caer bien. Si tan listos son, ¿por qué no averiguan cómo funciona la popularidad y sacan un diez, igual que en los exámenes?</para>
<para>Algunos argumentan que esto sería imposible, que los empollones caen mal porque los demás envidian su inteligencia y nada que hagan conseguirá que caigan bien. Ojalá fuera eso. Pues si mis compañeros de secundaria me envidiaban lo disimulaban muy bien. En cualquier caso, si la inteligencia fuese una cualidad envidiable, las chicas nos habrían preferido, dado que los chicos a los que los demás chicos envidian gustan a las chicas.</para>
<para>En los colegios a los que fui la inteligencia no importaba mucho. Ni se admiraba ni se despreciaba. Se prefería ser más inteligente que la media que menos, pero la inteligencia contaba menos que, por ejemplo, la apariencia física, el carisma o la aptitud para el deporte.</para>
<para>Entonces, si la inteligencia en sí no afecta a la popularidad, ¿por qué los empollones sistemáticamente caen mal? La respuesta, pienso yo, es que porque en realidad no desean ser populares.</para>
<para>Si alguien me hubiese dicho esto entonces me habría echado a reir. La impopularidad es un infierno para un niño, hasta el punto de que algunos llegan a suicidarse. Decirme que no deseaba ser popular equivaldría a decirle a alguien muriéndose de sed en un desierto que no quería un vaso de agua. Por supuesto que quería ser popular.</para>
<para>Pero no lo deseaba lo suficiente pues había algo que deseaba aún más: ser inteligente. No sólo sacar buenas notas, aunque eso algo me importaba, sino diseñar bellos cohetes, o escribir bien, o entender cómo se programa un ordenador. En general hacer cosas grandes.</para>
<para>Entonces nunca intentaba analizar mis deseos y compararlos. De lo contrario habría descubierto que ser inteligente me importaba más que otra cosa. Si me hubieran ofrecido ser el niño más popular pero a costa de tener una inteligencia media (modestia aparte), no habría aceptado.</para>
<para>Aunque sufren por caer mal, no creo que muchos hubiesen aceptado el trato. La idea de una inteligencia media les resulta insoportable. Pero la mayoría de los demás niños sí habrían aceptado el cambio. Para la mitad de ellos  habría supuesto una mejora. Incluso dentro del 20% superior (suponiendo, como todo el mundo pensaban entonces, que la inteligencia es unidimensional), ¿quién no hubiera renunciado a un 30% a cambio de que se lo quisiese y admirase?</para>
<para>Y ahí está, pienso yo, la raíz del problema. Los listos raros sirven a dos amos. Quieren caer bien, no cabe duda, pero aún más desean ser inteligentes. Y la popularidad no es una empresa que uno realiza en los descansos, desde luego no en el entorno ferozmente competitivo de un colegio de Secundaria estadounidense.</para>
 <!-- vertical space -->

 <!-- Alberti, arguably the archetype of the Renaissance Man, writes that
“no art, however minor, demands less than total dedication if you
want to excel in it.”1 I wonder if anyone in the world works harder
at anything than American school kids work at popularity. Navy
Seals and neurosurgery residents seem slackers by comparison.
They occasionally take vacations; some even have hobbies. An
American teenager may work at being popular every waking hour,
  365 days a year.-->
<para>Alberti, probablemente el arquetipo de Hombre Renacentista, escribió que <quote>todo arte, por menor que sea, exige una dedicación total si se aspira a sobresalir en él</quote>. Yo dudo de que nadie en este mundo se esfuerce más que los alumnos de una escuela estadounidense por mejorar su popularidad. Los marines y los residentes de neurocirugía resultan apáticos en comparación ya que ellos por lo menos alguna vez descansan y hasta tienen aficiones, mientras que un adolescente cuidará de su popularidad todas las horas del día los 365 días del año.</para>

<!--I don’t mean to suggest they do this consciously. Some of
them truly are little Machiavellis, but what I really mean here is
that teenagers are always on duty as conformists.
For example, teenage kids pay a great deal of attention to
clothes. They don’t consciously dress to be popular. They dress
to look good. But to who? To the other kids. Other kids’ opin-
ions become their definition of right, not just for clothes, but for
almost everything they do, right down to the way they walk. And
so every effort they make to do things “right” is also, consciously
  or not, an effort to be more popular.-->
    <para>No digo que lo hagan conscientemente. Aunque algunos de ellos son pequeños maquiavelos, lo que quiero decir es que todos se desviven por ir con la corriente. Por ejemplo, le prestan mucha atención a la ropa. No visten a drede para resultar populares, sino para fardar. ¿Fardar ante quién? Ante los demás adolescentes. La opinión de sus compañeros constituye lo correcto, no sólamente en ropa sino en casi todo lo que hacen, incluido cómo caminan. Por tanto todo esfuerzo que hacen por hacer lo <quote>correcto</quote> constituye, conscientemente o no, un esfuerzo por ser más populares.</para>
  
<!--Nerds don’t realize this. They don’t realize that it takes work
to be popular. In general, people outside some very demanding
field don’t realize the extent to which success depends on constant
(though often unconscious) effort. For example, most people seem
to consider the ability to draw as some kind of innate quality, like
being tall. In fact, most people who “can draw” like drawing, and
have spent many hours doing it; that’s why they’re good at it.
Likewise, popular isn’t just something you are or you aren’t, but
something you make yourself.-->
<para>Los empollones no lo comprenden. No imaginan el esfuerzo que cuesta ser popular. En general los que no participan en una actividad extenuante no saben hasta qué punto el éxito depende del esfuerzo constante y con frecuencia inconsciente. Por ejemplo, parece ser que la mayoría de la gente consideran saber dibujar como una cualidad innata, como ser alto. En la práctica a la mayoría de los que <quote>saben dibujar</quote> les gusta dibujar y le han dedicado muchas horas: por eso se les da bien.
  <!-- Gateway High School chess club, 1981. That’s me, upper left.-->
Igualmente, uno no nace popular ni no popular, sino que se hace.</para>
<!-- The main reason nerds are unpopular is that they have other
things to think about. Their attention is drawn to books or the
natural world, not fashions and parties. They’re like someone
trying to play soccer while balancing a glass of water on his head.
Other players who can focus their whole attention on the game
beat them effortlessly, and wonder why they seem so incapable.
Even if nerds cared as much as other kids about popularity,
being popular would be more work for them. The popular kids
learned to be popular, and to want to be popular, the same way
the nerds learned to be smart, and to want to be smart: from
their parents. While the nerds were being trained to get the right
  answers, the popular kids were being trained to please.-->
<para>La razón principal por la que los empollones no son populares es que les interesan otras cosas. Acaparan su atención los libros o el mundo natural, no la moda ni las fiestas. Son como alguien que se empeñara en jugar al fútbol llevando un vaso lleno de agua sobre la cabeza. Los demás jugadores que pueden poner toda su atención en el juego le superan fácilmente y se preguntan por qué se le da tan mal. Aunque a los empollones les importase la popularidad tanto como al resto, ser populares les costaría más que al resto. Los empollones aprenden a ser listos y lo desean igual que los populares aprenden a ser populares y lo desean: por influencia de sus padres. Mientas a los empollones les educaban para conocer la verdad, a los populares se les enseñaba a agradar.</para>
  
<!-- So far I’ve been finessing the relationship between smart and nerd,
using them as if they were interchangeable. In fact it’s only the
context that makes them so. A nerd is someone who isn’t socially
adept enough. But “enough” depends on where you are. In a
typical American school, standards for coolness are so high (or at
least, so specific) that you don’t have to be especially awkward to
  look awkward by comparison.-->
<para>He estado confundiendo la relación que hay entre listo y raro, empleándolos como sinónimos, cuando sólo determinado contexto los hace equivalentes. Un raro es alguien que no se desenvuelve suficientemente bien en sociedad. Pero <quote>suficientemente</quote> dependerá de dónde se encuentre uno, y en el típico colegio estadounidense el listón está tan alto (o al menos es tan específico) que no hace falta ser especialmente torpe para parecer torpe.</para>
    
<!-- Few smart kids can spare the attention that popularity requires.
Unless they also happen to be good-looking, natural athletes, or
siblings of popular kids, they’ll tend to become nerds. And that’s
why smart people’s lives are worst between, say, the ages of eleven
and seventeen. Life at that age revolves far more around popularity
than before or after.-->
<para>Pocos de los inteligentes pueden dedicar la atención que la popularidad requiere. A menos que sean de nacimiento guapos, buenos deportistas o hermanos de adolescentes populares, los tacharán de raros. Y esa es la razón por la que los inteligentes lo pasan mal entre los once y los diecisiete años, las edades en las que la popularidad imporata más.</para>

<!-- Before that, kids’ lives are dominated by their parents, not by
other kids. Kids do care what their peers think in elementary
school, but this isn’t their whole life, as it later becomes.
Around the age of eleven, though, kids seem to start treating
their family as a day job. They create a new world among them-
selves, and standing in this world is what matters, not standing
in their family. Indeed, being in trouble in their family can win
  them points in the world they care about. -->
<para>Antes de esa edad sus vidas giran en torno a sus padres, no en torno a otros niños. Aunque les importan las opiniones de sus compañeros de primaria, no es lo único en sus vidas, como acaba siendo en la adolescencia. Sin embargo al llegar los once años, más o menos, empiezan a tratar a la familia como una carga. Crean un mundo entre ellos y su situación en él les importa más que la relación con la familia. Más aún, tener problemas en casa da puntos en ese otro mundo que les importa más.</para>
  
<!-- The problem is, the world these kids create for themselves is
at first a very crude one. If you leave a bunch of eleven-year-olds
to their own devices, what you get is Lord of the Flies. Like a lot
of American kids, I read this book in school. Presumably it was
not a coincidence. Presumably someone wanted to point out to
us that we were savages, and that we had made ourselves a cruel
and stupid world. This was too subtle for me. While the book
seemed entirely believable, I didn’t get the additional message. I
wish they had just told us outright that we were savages and our
world was stupid.-->
<para>El problema es que ese mundo creado es de primeras bastante salvaje. Si dejas que una pandilla de onceañeros se lo monten sólos acaban como en El Señor de las Moscas. Al igual que a muchos adolescentes estadounidenses me hicieron leer este libro. Sospecho que no es mera coincidencia. Sospecho que alquien pretendía hacernos ver que éramos salvajes y que nos habíamos construido un mundo cruel y estúpido. Esa sutileza se me escapaba entonces. Aunque la historia parecía perfectamente verosímil, no captaba este mensaje. Ojalá nos hubieran dicho a las claras que éramos unos salvajes y que nuestro mundo era estúpido.</para>
  
<!-- Nerds would find their unpopularity more bearable if it merely
caused them to be ignored. Unfortunately, to be unpopular in
school is to be actively persecuted.
Why? Once again, anyone currently in school might think this
a strange question to ask. How could things be any other way?
5hackers & painters
But they could be. Adults don’t normally persecute nerds. Why
  do teenage kids do it?-->
    <para>Los raros habríamos soportado mejor nuestra impopularidad si nos hubiesen dejado en paz, pero por desgracia suponía además que te perseguían. ¿Por qué? Igual que antes, a cualquiera que vaya al colegio aún le parecerá obvio. ¡De qué otra manera podría ser! Bueno, podría ser de otra manera. Los adultos no persiguen a los raros. ¿Por qué los adolescentes sí?</para>
    
<!-- Partly because teenagers are still half children, and many chil-
dren are just intrinsically cruel. Some torture nerds for the same
reason they pull the legs off spiders. Before you develop a con-
science, torture is amusing. -->
<para>En parte porque los adolescentes son aún medio niños, y muchos niños son intrínsecamente crueles. Se tortura a los raros por la misma razón por la que se le arrancan las patas a las arañas. Antes de tener una consciencia moral torturar es divertido.</para>
  
<!-- Another reason kids persecute nerds is to make themselves
feel better. When you tread water, you lift yourself up by pushing
water down. Likewise, in any social hierarchy, people unsure of
their own position will try to emphasize it by maltreating those
they think rank below. I’ve read that this is why poor whites in
the United States are the group most hostile to blacks.
But I think the main reason other kids persecute nerds is that
it’s part of the mechanism of popularity. Popularity is only partially
about individual attractiveness. It’s much more about alliances.
To become more popular, you need to be constantly doing things
that bring you close to other popular people, and nothing brings
people closer than a common enemy.-->
  <para>Otra razón por la que persiguen a los raros es para sentirse mejor. Cuando se anda sobre el agua uno se mantiene arriba a fuerza de empujar el agua hacia abajo. Igualmente, en toda jerarquía social los que se sienten inseguros de su situación la reforzarán maltratando a los que consideran inferiores. He leído que esa es la razón por la que los blancos pobres de Estados Unidos son el grupo más hostil a los negros.</para>
  <para>No obstante opino que la principal razón por la que los demás persiguen a los raros es que la persecución forma parte de la carrera por la popularidad. La popularidad no depende tanto del atractivo individual como de las alianzas. Para ser popular necesitas estar constantemente haciendo cosas que te acercan  a la clase de los populares, y nada mejor que un enemigo común.</para>
  
<!-- Like a politician who wants to distract voters from bad times
at home, you can create an enemy if there isn’t a real one. By
singling out and persecuting a nerd, a group of kids from higher
in the hierarchy create bonds between themselves. Attacking an
outsider makes them all insiders. This is why the worst cases of
bullying happen with groups. Ask any nerd: you get much worse
treatment from a group of kids than from any individual bully,
  however sadistic.-->
    <para>Igual que el político que en los malos tiempos distrae a los votantes inventando un enemigo ficticio si no existe. Los que están más alto en la jerarquía crean lazos tomándola con un raro. Atacar a un forastero los une. Por eso es por lo que los peores casos de matonería ocurren en los grupos. Cualquier raro te dirá que les trata peor un grupo de adolescente que el más sádico de los matones.</para>
    
<!-- If it’s any consolation to the nerds, it’s nothing personal. The
group of kids who band together to pick on you are doing the
same thing, and for the same reason, as a bunch of guys who get
together to go hunting. They don’t actually hate you. They just
need something to chase.-->
<para>Por si os sirve de consuelo a los raros, diré que en realidad nadie tiene nada contra vosotros. La panda de adolescentes que se alía para hostigaros hace lo mismo y con igual motivación que el grupo de hombres que se une para ir de caza. No os odian, sino que necesitan a alguien a quien perseguir.</para>
    
<!-- Because they’re at the bottom of the scale, nerds are a safe
target for the entire school. If I remember correctly, the most
popular kids don’t persecute nerds; they don’t need to stoop to
such things. Most of the persecution comes from kids lower down,
  the nervous middle classes.-->
    <para>Los raros constituyen un objetivo seguro para el colegio entero porque ocupan en lo más bajo de la escala social. Que yo recuerde, los chicos más populares no nos perseguían: no necesitan rebajarse a eso. La mayoría de los ataques provenían de niveles inferiores, las inseguras clases medias.</para>
  <!-- The trouble is, there are a lot of them. The distribution of
popularity is not a pyramid, but tapers at the bottom like a pear.
The least popular group is quite small. (I believe we were the only
D table in our cafeteria map.) So there are more people who want
  to pick on nerds than there are nerds.-->
    <para>El problema es que eran muchos. La jerarquía de la popularidad no es una pirámide sino que se adelgaza en la base. Los menos populares son muy pocos. (Creo que sólo había una mesa D en el comedor.) Así que había más matones que raros.</para>
<!-- As well as gaining points by distancing oneself from unpopular
kids, one loses points by being close to them. A woman I know
says that in high school she liked nerds, but was afraid to be seen
talking to them because the other girls would make fun of her.
Unpopularity is a communicable disease; kids too nice to pick on
  nerds will still ostracize them in self-defense.-->
<para>Igual que se ganan puntos distanciándose de los menos populares, se pierden puntos por estar cerca de ellos. Una conocida me ha contado que en el colegio le atraian los raros, pero le daba miedo que la vieran hablando con ellos no sea que las demás chicas se burlasen. La impopularidad es una enfermedad contagiosa. Los adolescentes demasiado bondadosos como para meterse con ellos los evitarán en defensa propia.</para>
    
<!-- It’s no wonder, then, that smart kids tend to be unhappy in
middle school and high school. Their other interests leave them
little attention to spare for popularity, and since popularity re-
sembles a zero-sum game, this in turn makes them targets for
the whole school. And the strange thing is, this nightmare sce-
nario happens without any conscious malice, merely because of
  the shape of the situation.-->
    <para>No ha de extrañar por tanto que los más listos tiendan a pasarlo mal en el colegio. Sus otras aficiones acaparan la energía que podrían dedicar a conseguir popularidad, y dado que la popularidad al parecer como una <firstterm>suma cero</firstterm>, se convierten en blanco de todo el colegio. Y lo más curioso es que esta pesadilla ocurre sin ninguna malicia consciente, tan sólo por cómo es la situación.</para>
    
<!-- For me the worst stretch was junior high, when kid culture was
new and harsh, and the specialization that would later gradually
separate the smarter kids had barely begun. Nearly everyone I’ve
talked to agrees: the nadir is somewhere between eleven and four-
  teen.-->
    <para>Yo pasé la peor época en la primera etapa de secundaria, cuando la cultura adolescente era aún reciente y primitiva y la especializacion que después pondría a los listos en clases separadas apenas había empezado. Casi todo el mundo con el que lo he hablado coincide en que el punto más bajo ocurre entonces.</para>
    
<!--In our school it was eighth grade, which was ages twelve and
thirteen for me. There was a brief sensation that year when one
of our teachers overheard a group of girls waiting for the school
bus, and was so shocked that the next day she devoted the whole
  class to an eloquent plea not to be so cruel to one another. -->
    <para>En nuestro colegio lo peor era octavo curso, con edades entre doce y trece años. Ese año hubo una pequeña conmoción cuando una profesora escuchó la conversación de un grupo de chicas mientras esperaban el autobús de ruta y se impresionó tanto que al día siguiente emplear gastar la clase entera en un elocuente alegato en contra de la crueldad entre nosotros.</para>
    
<!-- It didn’t have any noticeable effect. What struck me at the time
was that she was surprised. You mean she doesn’t know the kind
  of things they say to one another? You mean this isn’t normal?-->
    <para>No surtió mucho efecto. En esa época lo que me llamó la atención es que a ella le sorprendiera. ¿No sabía qué clase de cosas se decían? ¿Que no es la norma?</para>
    
<!--It’s important to realize that, no, the adults don’t know what
the kids are doing to one another. They know, in the abstract,
that kids are monstrously cruel to one another, just as we know
7hackers & painters
in the abstract that people get tortured in poorer countries. But,
like us, they don’t like to dwell on this depressing fact, and they
don’t see evidence of specific abuses unless they go looking for it.-->
<para>Debemos darnos cuenta de que no, los adultos desconocen cómo se tratan los adolescentes entre sí. Saben, en abstracto, que somos monstruosamente crueles los unos con los otros, igual que sabemos en abstracto que en los países más pobres se tortura. Pero igual que nosotros prefieren no investigar este asunto tan deprimente y no ven pruebas de abusos concretos a menos que las busquen.</para>

<!-- Public school teachers are in much the same position as prison
wardens. Wardens’ main concern is to keep the prisoners on the
premises. They also need to keep them fed, and as far as possible
prevent them from killing one another. Beyond that, they want
to have as little to do with the prisoners as possible, so they leave
them to create whatever social organization they want. From what
I’ve read, the society that the prisoners create is warped, savage,
and pervasive, and it is no fun to be at the bottom of it.-->
<para>Los profesores de secundaria están en situación parecida a la de los funcionarios de cárceles, cuyo principal objetivo es que no se escapen los presos. También los tienen que alimentar y, en la medida de lo posible, evitar que se maten entre ellos. Por lo demás quieren tener cuanto menos trato con los presos mejor, por lo que les dejan crear cualquier organización social que elijan. Y por lo que he leído las sociedades que crean son distorsionadas, salvajes, oprimentes y no es nada divertido estar en el punto más bajo de ellas.</para>

<!-- In outline, it was the same at the schools I went to. The most
important thing was to stay on the premises. While there, the au-
thorities fed you, prevented overt violence, and made some effort
to teach you something. But beyond that they didn’t want to have
too much to do with the kids. Like prison wardens, the teachers
mostly left us to ourselves. And, like prisoners, the culture we
created was barbaric. -->
  <para>En líneas generales ocurría lo mismo en los colegios a los que fui. Lo más importante erea mantenernos dentro del recinto. Allí las autoridades nos alimentaban, evitaban toda violencia manifiesta y se esforzaban por enseñarnos algo. Más allá de eso preferían no implicarse demasiado con nosotros. Igual que los guardas de prisión, los profesores nos dejaban hacer. E igual que los presos, la sociedad que creábamos era brutal.</para>  
  
  <!-- vertical space -->
  
<!-- Why is the real world more hospitable to nerds? It might seem
that the answer is simply that it’s populated by adults, who are too
mature to pick on one another. But I don’t think this is true. Adults
in prison certainly pick on one another. And so, apparently, do
society wives; in some parts of Manhattan, life for women sounds
like a continuation of high school, with all the same petty intrigues. -->
<para>¿Por qué en el mundo real se trata mejor a los raros que entre adolescentes? Podría parecer que la explicación es porque está formado por adultos, demasiado maduros como para meterse los unos con los otros. Yo no pienso así. Los adultos de las cárceles se meten los unos con los otros. Lo mismo ocurre al parecer entre algunas amas de casa. En ciertas partes de Manhattan la vida de una mujer parece la continuación de la secundaria, con las mismas mezquinas intrigas.</para>
 
<!-- I think the important thing about the real world is not that
it’s populated by adults, but that it’s very large, and the things you
do have real effects. That’s what school, prison, and ladies-who-
lunch all lack. The inhabitants of all those worlds are trapped in
little bubbles where nothing they do can have more than a local
effect. Naturally these societies degenerate into savagery. They
  have no function for their form to follow.-->
<para>Pienso que el factor principal del mundo real no es que está formado por adultos sino que es muy grande y las acciones tienen consecuencias reales. Eso es lo que falta en los colegios, cárceles y círculos de casadas, cuyos miembros están atrapados en pequeñas burbujas donde nada de lo que hacen repercute en el exterior. Es natural que estas sociedades en el salvajismo. No hay una función que su estructura deba realizar.</para>
    
<!-- When the things you do have real effects, it’s no longer enough
just to be pleasing. It starts to be important to get the right an-
swers, and that’s where nerds show to advantage. Bill Gates will of
8why nerds are unpopular
course come to mind. Though notoriously lacking in social skills,
  he gets the right answers, at least as measured in revenue.-->
<para>Cuando nuestras acciones tienen efectos reales ya no basta con que resulten agradables. Empieza a importar y a valorarse el conocimiento, y ahí es donde los raros sobresalen. Se me ocurre el ejemplo de Bill Gates que, aunque sea torpe en sociedad, posee unos conocimientos válidos, o al menos eso indica su nivel de ingresos.</para>

<!-- The other thing that’s different about the real world is that it’s
much larger. In a large enough pool, even the smallest minorities
can achieve a critical mass if they clump together. Out in the real
world, nerds collect in certain places and form their own soci-
eties where intelligence is the most important thing. Sometimes
the current even starts to flow in the other direction: sometimes,
particularly in university math and science departments, nerds de-
liberately exaggerate their awkwardness in order to seem smarter.
John Nash so admired Norbert Wiener that he adopted his habit
  of touching the wall as he walked down a corridor.-->
<para>La otra diferencia con el mundo real es que es más grande. En un grupo suficientemente grande hasta la más ínfima de las minorías puede alcanzar una masa crítica si se une. En el mundo real los raros se juntan en determinados lugares y forman sociedades donde se valora la inteligencia más que otra cosa. A veces la corriente incluso empieza a fluir en sentido contrario: a veces, sobre todo en los departamentos de matemáticas y ciencia de la universidad, los raros exageran su torpeza a drede a fin de parecer más listos. John Nash admiraba tanto a Norbert Wiener que copió su costumbre de caminar por los pasillos tentando la pared.</para>
  
    <!-- vertical space -->

<!-- As a thirteen-year-old kid, I didn’t have much more experience of
the world than what I saw immediately around me. The warped
little world we lived in was, I thought, the world. The world seemed
cruel and boring, and I’m not sure which was worse.-->
<para>A los trece años no tenía apenas más experiencia del mundo que lo que me rodeaba físicamente. Pensaba que la realidad distorsionada en que vivía el único mundo. Resultaba cruel y aburrido, y no sé cuál de las dos cosas es peor.</para>
    
<!-- Because I didn’t fit into this world, I thought that something
must be wrong with me. I didn’t realize that the reason we nerds
didn’t fit in was that in some ways we were a step ahead. We were
already thinking about the kind of things that matter in the real
world, instead of spending all our time playing an exacting but
mostly pointless game like the others.-->
<para>Como yo no encajaba en él pensaba que yo estaba mal hecho. No me daba cuenta de que la razón por la que los raros no encajábamos era porque en cierto sentido íbamos un paso por delante. Nos interesaban ya las cosas que en el mundo real importan, en lugar de participar a tiempo completo en un juego absorbente y sin sentido como hacían los demás.</para>

<!-- We were a bit like an adult would be if he were thrust back
into middle school. He wouldn’t know the right clothes to wear,
the right music to like, the right slang to use. He’d seem to the
kids a complete alien. The thing is, he’d know enough not to care
  what they thought. We had no such confidence.-->
<para>Éramos un poco como un adulto que volviera a la Secundaria. No sabría qué ropa hay que llevar, qué música escuchar, qué argot hablar. Los adolescentes le considerarían un forastero. Lo importante es que sabría estar por encima de las opiniones de esos compañeros, pero nosotros no teníamos tanta seguridad en nosotros mismos.</para>

<!-- A lot of people seem to think it’s good for smart kids to be
thrown together with “normal” kids at this stage of their lives.
Perhaps. But in at least some cases the reason the nerds don’t fit
in really is that everyone else is crazy. I remember sitting in the
audience at a “pep rally” at my high school, watching as the cheer-
leaders threw an effigy of an opposing player into the audience to
9hackers & painters
be torn to pieces. I felt like an explorer witnessing some bizarre
  tribal ritual.-->
    <para>Observo que mucha gente opina que conviene obligar a los adolescentes listos a mezclarse con los <quote>normales</quote> en esa etapa de su vida. Tal vez. Pero al menos en algunos casos la razón por la que los raros no encajan es más bien que el resto están locos. Me acuerdo de una vez que presencié un espectáculo antes de un partido de mi colegio en el que l@s animador@s arrojaron a los asistentes la efigie de un jugador contrario para que la hicieran trizas. Me sentí como el explorador que presencia un macabro ritual tribal.</para>
    
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- If I could go back and give my thirteen year old self some advice,
the main thing I’d tell him would be to stick his head up and look
around. I didn’t really grasp it at the time, but the whole world
we lived in was as fake as a Twinkie. Not just school, but the
entire town. Why do people move to suburbia? To have kids! So
no wonder it seemed boring and sterile. The whole place was a
giant nursery, an artificial town created explicitly for the purpose
  of breeding children.-->
    <para>Si pudiese regresar al pasado y dar un consejo al niño de trece años que fui, le diría que abriera bien los ojos y mirara alrededor. Entonces no me daba cuenta de que el mundo en que vivíamos era más falso que un blanco pasando por indio. No digo la escuela, sino la ciudad entera. ¿Por qué la gente se muda a urbanizaciones? ¡Para tener hijos! Por tanto, no ha de extrañar que todo resultara aburrido y estéril. El barrio entero formaba una inmensa guardería, una ciudad artificial creada ex profeso para criar niños.</para>
    
<!-- Where I grew up, it felt as if there was nowhere to go, and
nothing to do. This was no accident. Suburbs are deliberately
designed to exclude the outside world, because it contains things
  that could endanger children.-->
<para>Donde me crié no parecía que hubiera ningún sitio a dónde ir ni nada que hacer. Esto no es casual. Estas urbanizaciones se diseñan para excluir el mundo exterior, del que podrían venir cosas peligrosas para los niños.</para>

<!-- And as for the schools, they were just holding pens within this
fake world. Officially the purpose of schools is to teach kids. In
fact their primary purpose is to keep kids locked up in one place
for a big chunk of the day so adults can get things done. And I
have no problem with this: in a specialized industrial society, it
  would be a disaster to have kids running around loose.-->
    <para>Los colegios a su vez eran meros recintos de contención dentro de este falso mundo, aunque oficialmente existieran para instruirnos. En realidad su propósito principal era encenrarnos en un sitio una buena parte del día para que los adultos pudieran realizar sus asuntos. Y lo acepto: en una sociedad industrial especializada sería desastrosos dejar que los niños corretearan por todas partes.</para>
    
<!-- What bothers me is not that the kids are kept in prisons, but
that (a) they aren’t told about it, and (b) the prisons are run mostly
by the inmates. Kids are sent off to spend six years memorizing
meaningless facts in a world ruled by a caste of giants who run
after an oblong brown ball, as if this were the most natural thing
in the world. And if they balk at this surreal cocktail, they’re called
  misfits.-->
    <para>Lo que me preocupa no es que se tenga a los niños encarcelados, sino que (a) no se les informe de esto, y (b) que las cárceles las dirijan los mismos presos. Se envía a los niños a memorizar seis años seguidos datos sin sentido en un mundo gobernado po9r una casta de gigantes que corren tras una pelota alargada, como si fuera lo màs natural del mundo. Y si rehúsan participar en esta función surrealista se les tacha de inadaptados.</para>
  
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- Life in this twisted world is stressful for the kids. And not just for
  the nerds. Like any war, it’s damaging even to the winners.-->
    <para>Vivir en este mundo retorcido resulta estresante para los niños. Como toda guerra, perjudica incluso a los vencedores.</para>
    
<!-- Adults can’t avoid seeing that teenage kids are tormented. So
why don’t they do something about it? Because they blame it
on puberty. The reason kids are so unhappy, adults tell them-
10why nerds are unpopular
selves, is that monstrous new chemicals, hormones, are now cours-
ing through their bloodstream and messing up everything. There’s
nothing wrong with the system; it’s just inevitable that kids will
  be miserable at that age.-->
  <para>Los adultos no pueden evitar ver que se atormenta a los adolescentes. ¿Entonces por qué no hacen nada? Porque lo achacan a la pubertad. Según su versión, los niños los pasan mal porque unas substancias horribles llamadas hormonas les corren por la sangre causando estragos. El problema no es el sistema y que lo pasen mal a esas edades es inevitable.</para>
    
<!-- This idea is so pervasive that even the kids believe it, which
probably doesn’t help. Someone who thinks his feet naturally hurt
is not going to stop to consider the possibility that he is wearing
  the wrong size shoes.-->
    <para>Esta explicación está tan difundida que hasta los adolescentes se la creen, lo cuál es perjudicial. Si a alguien le duelen los pies y piensa que es natural no va a pararse a averiguar si lleva su talla de zapato.</para>
    
<!-- I’m suspicious of this theory that thirteen-year-old kids are
intrinsically messed up. If it’s physiological, it should be universal.
Are Mongol nomads all nihilists at thirteen? I’ve read a lot of
history, and I have not seen a single reference to this supposedly
universal fact before the twentieth century. Teenage apprentices
in the Renaissance seem to have been cheerful and eager. They got
in fights and played tricks on one another of course (Michelangelo
  had his nose broken by a bully), but they weren’t crazy.-->
<para>No me convence esta teoría de que los treceañeros están trastornados intrínsecamente. Si se tratara de un problema fisiológico sería mundial. ¿Son todos los nómadas mongoles nihilistas a los trece años? He leído mucha historia y no he encontrado ni una sola alusión a este fenómeno supuestamente general antes del siglo XX. Los aprendices adolescentes del Renacimiento por lo visto eran alegres y curiosos. También se peleaban y si gastaban romas pesadas -a Miguel Ángel le partió la nariz un matón- pero no estaban locos.</para>

<!-- As far as I can tell, the concept of the hormone-crazed teenager
is coeval with suburbia. I don’t think this is a coincidence. I think
teenagers are driven crazy by the life they’re made to lead. Teenage
apprentices in the Renaissance were working dogs. Teenagers now
are neurotic lapdogs. Their craziness is the craziness of the idle
  everywhere.-->
<para>Por lo que sé el concepto de adolescente intoxicado de hormonas es coetáneo con el fenómeno de las zonas residenciales. No creo que sea mera coincidencia. Pienso que los adolescentes enloquecen por el tipo de vida que se les obliga a llevar. Los aprendices adolescentes renacentistas trabajaban como chinos. Los adolescentes de ahora son perros falderos y su locura se asemeja a la de los ociosos de cualquier parte.</para>
  
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- When I was in school, suicide was a constant topic among the
smarter kids. No one I knew did it, but several planned to, and
some may have tried. Mostly this was just a pose. Like other
teenagers, we loved the dramatic, and suicide seemed very dra-
matic. But partly it was because our lives were at times genuinely
  miserable.-->
<para>Cuando iba al colegio constantemente salía el tema del suicidio. Ninguno de mis conocidos se suicidó, pero varios planeaban hacerlo, y algunos tal vez lo intentaran. En la mayoría de los casos no se trataba más que de una pose. Como muchos adolescentes, nos atraía lo melodramático, y el suicidio colmaba estas aspiraciones. Pero en parte se debía a que a veces lo pasábamos verdaderamente mal.</para>
    
<!-- Bullying was only part of the problem. Another problem, and
possibly an even worse one, was that we never had anything real
to work on. Humans like to work; in most of the world, your
work is your identity. And all the work we did was pointless, or
  seemed so at the time.-->
    <para>Los matones no eran más que uno de los problemas. Otro, probablemente aún peor, era que nunca teníamos nada real que realizar. A los seres humanos les gusta trabajar. En casi todas partes el trabajo es su identidad. Pero todo trabajo que hacíamos carecía de sentido, o al menos eso nos parecía entonces.</para>
    
    <!-- 11hackers & painters -->
    
<!-- At best it was practice for real work we might do far in the
future, so far that we didn’t even know at the time what we were
practicing for. More often it was just an arbitrary series of hoops to
jump through, words without content designed mainly for testa-
bility. (The three main causes of the Civil War were. . . . Test: List
  the three main causes of the Civil War.)-->
    <para>En el mejor de los casos servía de práctica para trabajo que podriamos realizar en el mundo real en un futuro lejano, tan lejano que entonces no sabíamos para qué practicábamos. La mayoría de las veces consistía en una serie de obstáculos que había que salvar, palabras vacias escogidas principalmente para que se nos pudiera examinar de ellas. (Las tres causas principales de la Guerra Civil fueron... Pregunta: enumera las tres causas principales de la Guerra Civil.)</para>
    
<!-- And there was no way to opt out. The adults had agreed among
themselves that this was to be the route to college. The only way
  to escape this empty life was to submit to it.-->
    <para>Y no había escapatoria. Los adultos habían acordado que por ahí había que pasar para acceder a la universidad. La única manera de superar esta existencia vacía era someterse a ella.</para>
    
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- Teenage kids used to have a more active role in society. In pre-
industrial times, they were all apprentices of one sort or another,
whether in shops or on farms or even on warships. They weren’t
left to create their own societies. They were junior members of
  adult societies.-->
    <para>Antes los adolescentes participaban más en la sociedad. Antes de la Revolución Industrial eran todos aprendices de algo, en talleres, en el campo o incluso en buques de guerra. No se les permitía crear sus propias sociedades. Eran miembros jóvenes de sociedades adultas.</para>
      
<!-- Teenagers seem to have respected adults more then, because
the adults were the visible experts in the skills they were trying to
learn. Now most kids have little idea what their parents do in their
distant offices, and see no connection (indeed, there is precious
  little) between schoolwork and the work they’ll do as adults.-->
    <para>Al parecer aquellos adolescentes respetaban a los adultos más que ahora, pues eran los expertos que conocían en las destrezas que trataban de aprender. Hoy en día la mayoría de los adolescentes apenas saben qué hacen sus padres en sus remotas oficinas, y no ven ninguna relación (poca hay) entre tareas escolares y el trabajo que realizarán de adultos.</para>
    
<!-- And if teenagers respected adults more, adults also had more
use for teenagers. After a couple years’ training, an apprentice
could be a real help. Even the newest apprentice could be made
  to carry messages or sweep the workshop.-->
    <para>Y si los adolescentes respetaban a los adultos más, los adultos les encargaban más trabajo. Tras un par de años de formación un aprendiz podía ser útil. Incluso el principiante podía llevar mensajes o barrer el suelo.</para>
    
<!-- Now adults have no immediate use for teenagers. They would
be in the way in an office. So they drop them off at school on their
way to work, much as they might drop the dog off at a kennel if
  they were going away for the weekend.-->
    <para>Hoy en día los adultos no les encargan nada a los adolescentes. En una oficina estorbarían. Por tanto los dejan en el colegio de camino al trabajo igual que llevamos a un perro en la perrera antes de salir de vacaciones.</para>
    
<!-- What happened? We’re up against a hard one here. The cause
of this problem is the same as the cause of so many present ills:
specialization. As jobs become more specialized, we have to train
longer for them. Kids in pre-industrial times started working at
about 14 at the latest; kids on farms, where most people lived,
began far earlier. Now kids who go to college don’t start working
12why nerds are unpopular
full-time till 21 or 22. With some degrees, like MDs and PhDs,
  you may not finish your training till 30.-->
    <para>¿A qué se debe esto? La cuestión es complicada. La causa del problema es la misma que la de muchos otros males contemporáneos: la especialización. A medida que los trabajos se vuelven más especializados necesitamos formarnos más tiempo para desempeñarlos. En la era preindustrial se empezaba a trabajar a los 14 años como muy tarde. En el campo, donde vivía la mayoría, mucho antes. Ahora un adolescente que vaya a la universidad no consigue un verdadero empleo hasta los 21 ó 22. En algunos casos, como el de los másteres y doctorados, uno no acaba de formarse hasta los 30.</para>
    
<!-- Teenagers now are useless, except as cheap labor in industries
like fast food, which evolved to exploit precisely this fact. In almost
any other kind of work, they’d be a net loss. But they’re also too
young to be left unsupervised. Someone has to watch over them,
and the most efficient way to do this is to collect them together
  in one place. Then a few adults can watch all of them.-->
    <para>Ahora los adolescentes no valen para nada, salvo como mano de obra barata en sectores como el de la comida rápida, que surgió precisamente para aprovechar esta circunstancia. En casi cualquier otro trabajo serían más un estorbo que una ayuda. Pero tampoco se los puede dejar solos sino que hay que vigilarlos, y la manera más eficiente es juntarlos en un solo sitio en el que unos pocos adultos puedan vigilarlos.</para>
    
<!-- If you stop there, what you’re describing is literally a prison,
albeit a part-time one. The problem is, many schools practically
do stop there. The stated purpose of schools is to educate the
kids. But there is no external pressure to do this well. And so
most schools do such a bad job of teaching that the kids don’t
really take it seriously—not even the smart kids. Much of the
time we were all, students and teachers both, just going through
  the motions.-->
    <para>Hasta el momento he descrito algo idéntico a una cárcel a tiempo parcial. El problema es que muchos colegios no van mucho más allá. El propósito oficial de los colegios es formar a los alumnos, pero no se ejerce una presión desde fuera para que se haga esto bien. Al final en la mayoría de los colegios se enseña tan mal que ni siquiera los inteligentes se toman en serio los estudios. La mayoría de las veces todos, alumnos y profesores, no hacíamos más que cubrir las apariencias.</para>
    
<!-- In my high school French class we were supposed to read
Hugo’s Les Miserables. I don’t think any of us knew French well
enough to make our way through this enormous book. Like the
rest of the class, I just skimmed the Cliff ’s Notes. When we were
given a test on the book, I noticed that the questions sounded odd.
They were full of long words that our teacher wouldn’t have used.
Where had these questions come from? From the Cliff ’s Notes,
it turned out. The teacher was using them too. We were all just
  pretending.-->
    <para>En mi colegio en clase de francés se suponía que leíamos Les Miserables, de Hugo. No creo que ninguno supiera suficiente francés como para digerir libro tan largo. Igual que el resto, me limité a hojear las Anotaciones de Cliff. Cuando nos pusieron el examen me extrañaron las preguntas. Se formulaban con palabras complicadas que nuestra profesora no empleaba. ¿De dónde habría sacado esas preguntas? Pues de las Anotaciones de Cliff, según resultó. La profesora también las utilizaba. Estábamos todos fingiendo.</para>
    
<!-- There are certainly great public school teachers. The energy
and imagination of my fourth grade teacher, Mr. Mihalko, made
that year something his students still talk about, thirty years later.
But teachers like him were individuals swimming upstream. They
  couldn’t fix the system.-->
    <para>No dudo de que hay excelentes profesores de Secundaria. Los alumnos de cuarto de Don Mihalko aún hoy comentan su energía e imaginación, treinta años después. Pero esos profesores eran individualidades nadando contra corriente que no podían arreglar solos el sistema.</para>
  
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- In almost any group of people you’ll find hierarchy. When groups
of adults form in the real world, it’s generally for some common
purpose, and the leaders end up being those who are best at it. The
13hackers & painters
problem with most schools is, they have no purpose. But hierarchy
  there must be. And so the kids make one out of nothing.-->
    <para>En casi todo grupo encontramos una jerarquía. Cuando los adultos forman grupos en el mundo real suele ser para un fin común, y acaban siendo jefes los mejores para ello. El problema de la mayoría de los colegios es que no tienen ningún fin. Pero como jerarquía tiene que haber, los alumnos crean una de la nada.</para>
    
<!-- We have a phrase to describe what happens when rankings
have to be created without any meaningful criteria. We say that
the situation degenerates into a popularity contest. And that’s exactly
what happens in most American schools. Instead of depending
on some real test, one’s rank depends mostly on one’s ability to
increase one’s rank. It’s like the court of Louis XIV. There is no
  external opponent, so the kids become one another’s opponents.-->
    <para>Tenemos una expresión que describe lo que ocurre cuando hay que crear una jerarquía sin que haya un criterio con sentido. Decimos que la situación <quote>degenera en un concurso de popularidad</quote>. Y eso precisamente pasa en la mayoría de los colegios estadounidenses. En lugar de basarse en pruebas objetivas, la categoría de uno depende de su capacidad de ascender. Parece la corte de Luis XIV. En ausencia de competidores externos cada adolescente se enfrenta a los demás.</para>
    
<!-- When there is some real external test of skill, it isn’t painful
to be at the bottom of the hierarchy. A rookie on a football team
doesn’t resent the skill of the veteran; he hopes to be like him one
day and is happy to have the chance to learn from him. The veteran
may in turn feel a sense of noblesse oblige. And most importantly,
their status depends on how well they do against opponents, not
on whether they can push the other down.-->
<para>Cuando existe un criterio externo de vaĺía los que están más abajo no lo pasan mal. El novato de un equipo de rugby acepta la destreza del veterano. Aspira a ser como él algún día y se alegra de tener un modelo. El veterano por su parte asumirá su responsabilidad con los inferiores. Y sobre todo que su categoría dependerá del éxito frente al enemigo, no de hundir al compañero.</para>

<!-- Court hierarchies are another thing entirely. This type of so-
ciety debases anyone who enters it. There is neither admiration
at the bottom, nor noblesse oblige at the top. It’s kill or be killed.-->
<para>No así en las jerarquías de corte, un tipo de sociedad que degrada a todo el que entra en ella. Ni los de abajo admiran a los de arriba, ni éstos se sienten responsables de los otros. Se trata de matar o morir.</para>

<!-- This is the sort of society that gets created in American sec-
ondary schools. And it happens because these schools have no
real purpose beyond keeping the kids all in one place for a cer-
tain number of hours each day. What I didn’t realize at the time,
and in fact didn’t realize till very recently, is that the twin horrors
of school life, the cruelty and the boredom, both have the same
  cause.-->
    <para>Éste es el tipo de sociedad que se crea en los colegios estadounidenses, y se debe a que no persiguen otra finalidad que mantener a los alumnos dentro de un recinto un número dado de horas al día. Lo que no sospechaba entonces y no he comprendido hasta hace poco es que el horror doble de la crueldad y el aburrimiento tenían la misma causa.</para>
  
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- The mediocrity of American public schools has worse consequen-
ces than just making kids unhappy for six years. It breeds a re-
belliousness that actively drives kids away from the things they’re
  supposed to be learning.-->
    <para>La mediocridad de nuestros colegios tiene consecuencias peores que la de hacérnoslo pasar mal seis años. Genera una rebeldía que aleja a los alumnos de las materias que se supone que deberían aprender.</para>
    
<!-- Like many nerds, probably, it was years after high school before
I could bring myself to read anything we’d been assigned then. And
I lost more than books. I mistrusted words like “character” and
“integrity” because they had been so debased by adults. As they
14why nerds are unpopular
were used then, these words all seemed to mean the same thing:
obedience. The kids who got praised for these qualities tended to
be at best dull-witted prize bulls, and at worst facile schmoozers.
If that was what character and integrity were, I wanted no part of
  them.-->
    <para>Como muchos otros raros, tardé años en volver a leer libros que nos habian mandado. Me perdí los libros y más cosas. Desconfiaba de palabras tales como <quote>personalidad</quote> e <quote>integridad</quote> por lo mucho que los adultos las habían degradado. Tal como se empleaban entonces, todas parecían significar lo mismo: obediencia. Los alumnos en quienes se alababan estas cualidades solían ser como poco [ambiciosos y como mucho pelotas repugnantes]. Y eso era lo que significaban <quote>personalidad</quote> e <quote>integridad</quote>, prefería no tenerlas.</para>
    
<!-- The word I most misunderstood was “tact.” As used by adults,
it seemed to mean keeping your mouth shut. I assumed it was
derived from the same root as “tacit” and “taciturn,” and that it
literally meant being quiet. I vowed that I would never be tactful;
they were never going to shut me up. In fact, it’s derived from the
same root as “tactile,” and what it means is to have a deft touch.
Tactful is the opposite of clumsy. I don’t think I learned this until
  college.-->
    <para>La palabra que malinterpretaba más era <quote>tacto</quote>. Tal como la empleaban los adultos debían de significar mantener la boca cerrada. Imaginaba que provenía de la misma raíz que <quote>tácito</quote> y <quote>taciturno</quote>, y que significaba callarse. Juré no tener nunca tacto, que nunca me callarían. En realidad proviene de la misma raíz que <quote>táctil</quote> y significa toque hábil. Es lo contrario de torpe. No aprendí esto hasta que llegué a la universidad.</para>
    
<!-- Nerds aren’t the only losers in the popularity rat race. Nerds are
unpopular because they’re distracted. There are other kids who
deliberately opt out because they’re so disgusted with the whole
  process.-->
    <para>Los raros no són los únicos que pierden en la carrera por la popularidad. No agradan porque les ocupan otras cosas. Otros adolescentes se salen del sistema voluntariamente porque les repugna cómo funciona.</para>
<!-- Teenage kids, even rebels, don’t like to be alone, so when kids
opt out of the system, they tend to do it as a group. At the schools I
went to, the focus of rebellion was drug use, specifically marijuana.
The kids in this tribe wore black concert t-shirts and were called
  “freaks.”-->
    <para>Ni a los adolescentes, ni siquiera a los más rebeldes, les agrada estar solos, por tanto cuando se salen del sistema lo hacen grupos. En los colegios a que asistí la rebeldía se centraba en el consumo de drogas, marihuana en particular. Los miembros de esta tribu vestían camisetas negras de concierto y los llamábamos los <quote>friquis</quote>.</para>
    
<!-- Freaks and nerds were allies, and there was a good deal of
overlap between them. Freaks were on the whole smarter than
other kids, though never studying (or at least never appearing to)
was an important tribal value. I was more in the nerd camp, but
I was friends with a lot of freaks.-->
  <para>Los friquis y los raros éramos aliados y estábamos algo mezclados. Los friquis eran por regla general más inteligentes que el resto, pero no estudiar (o por lo menos disimularlo) era uno de sus principales valores tribales. Yo estaba más cerca de los raros, pero me llevaba bien con muchos friquis.</para>
  
<!-- They used drugs, at least at first, for the social bonds they
created. It was something to do together, and because the drugs
  were illegal, it was a shared badge of rebellion.-->
    <para>Consumían drogas, al menos al principio, para crear vínculos sociales. Era algo que se hacía en comunidad, y como eran ilegales, constituían una marca de rebeliión.</para>
    
<!-- I’m not claiming that bad schools are the whole reason kids
get into trouble with drugs. After a while, drugs have their own
momentum. No doubt some of the freaks ultimately used drugs to
escape from other problems—trouble at home, for example. But,
in my school at least, the reason most kids started using drugs
was rebellion. Fourteen-year-olds didn’t start smoking pot be-
cause they’d heard it would help them forget their problems. They
  started because they wanted to join a different tribe.-->
    <para>No quiero decir con esto que los adolescentes tengan problemas de drogadicción por culpa de los malos colegios. Pasado un tiempo pierden fuerza. No cabe duda de que algunos de estos consumidores acabaron usándolas para evadirse de otros problemas, domésticos por ejemplo. Pero al menos en mi colegio la razón por la que la mayoría de ellos empezaron a consumirlas era la rebeldía. No se ponían a fumar hierba a sus catorce años porque hubiesen oído que te ayuda a olvidar los problemas. Lo hacían para entrar en otra tribu.</para>
    
<!-- Misrule breeds rebellion; this is not a new idea. And yet the
authorities still for the most part act as if drugs were themselves
  the cause of the problem.-->
    <para>Que el mal gobierno genera rebelión no me lo he inventado yo. Y sin embargo las autoridades por lo general actúan como si las drogas fueran la causa del problema.</para>
    
    <!-- vertical space -->
    
<!-- The real problem is the emptiness of school life. We won’t see
solutions till adults realize that. The adults who may realize it
first are the ones who were themselves nerds in school. Do you
want your kids to be as unhappy in eighth grade as you were? I
wouldn’t. Well, then, is there anything we can do to fix things?
Almost certainly. There is nothing inevitable about the current
system. It has come about mostly by default.2 -->
<para>El verdadero problema es el vacío de la vida escolar. No veremos mejoras hasta que los adultos se conciencien de esto. Tal vez los primeros que caigan en la cuenta sean los que en el colegio fueron raros. ¿Queremos que nuestros hijos lo pasen tan mal en octavo como nosotros? Yo no. Entonces, ¿podemos hacer algo para evitarlo? Casi seguro que sí. No hay nada inamovible en el actual sistema. Ha surgido casi por pura inercia.</para>
<!-- Adults, though, are busy. Showing up for school plays is one
thing. Taking on the educational bureaucracy is another. Perhaps
a few will have the energy to try to change things. I suspect the
hardest part is realizing that you can.-->
<para>Pero los adultos están ocupados. Asistir a las obras de teatro de los críos no cuesta tanto, pero hacerse cargo a la burocracia de la enseñanza sí. Tal vez algunos tengan la energía de intentar cambiarla. Supongo que lo más difícil es comprender que sí se puede.</para>
<!-- Nerds still in school should not hold their breath. Maybe one
day a heavily armed force of adults will show up in helicopters to
rescue you, but they probably won’t be coming this month. Any
immediate improvement in nerds’ lives is probably going to have
  to come from the nerds themselves.-->
    <para>Los raros de todos los colegios no deberían hacerse ilusiones. Tal vez algún día llegue para rescatarlos una fuerza armada de adultos en helicópteros, pero probablemente no ocurra este mes. Toda mejora a corto plazo en sus vidas dependerá de ellos mismos.</para>
<!-- Merely understanding the situation they’re in should make it
less painful. Nerds aren’t losers. They’re just playing a different
game, and a game much closer to the one played in the real world.
Adults know this. It’s hard to find successful adults now who don’t
claim to have been nerds in high school.-->
<para>Comprender la situación en que se hallan debería proporcionarles cierto alivio. No son perdedores, sino que sencillamente participan en un juego distinto mucho más parecido al que se juega en el mundo real. Los adultos lo saben. No se encuentran muchos adultos competentes hoy en día que no se quejen de haber sido de los raros en el colegio.</para>
<!-- It’s important for nerds to realize, too, that school is not life.
School is a strange, artificial thing, half sterile and half feral. It’s
all-encompassing, like life, but it isn’t the real thing. It’s only
temporary, and if you look, you can see beyond it even while you’re
still in it.-->
<para>Los raros también deben comprender que la escuela no es la vida, sino un mundo extraño y artificial, medio esteril y medio animal. Es absorbente, como la vida, pero no es auténtico. Es temporal y, esforzándose uno puede ver algo más allá.</para>
<!-- If life seems awful to kids, it’s neither because hormones are
turning you all into monsters (as your parents believe), nor because
life actually is awful (as you believe). It’s because the adults, who
no longer have any economic use for you, have abandoned you
to spend years cooped up together with nothing real to do. Any
society of that type is awful to live in. You don’t have to look any
further to explain why teenage kids are unhappy.-->
  <para>Si los adolescentes lo pasan mal, no es por culpa de que las hormonas les estén volviendo unos monstruitos (como muchos padres creen), ni porque la vida sea mala (como creéis vosotros). Es porque los adultos, para los que ya no tenéis un valor económico, os condenan a pasar años encerrados juntos sin nada sustancial que hacer. Toda sociedad así planteada resulta invivible. No busquéis otra explicación a la infelicidad de los adolescentes.</para>
<!-- I’ve said some harsh things in this essay, but really the thesis
is an optimistic one—that several problems we take for granted
are in fact not insoluble after all. Teenage kids are not inherently
unhappy monsters. That should be encouraging news to kids and
adults both. -->
  <para>En este ensayo he dicho algunas cosas duras, pero en el fondo mi tesis es optimista: muchos problemas que damos por imposibles en realidad pueden solucionarse. Los adolescentes no son necesariamente monstruos infelices. Esto les debería dar ánimos tanto a ellos como a los adultos.</para>
 
</section>